Research data shall be free, digital, shared and re-usable.
Only while open it will reach its true potential.
Fostering collaboration, open data accelerates research,
and even years after its production, by allowing easy preliminary and meta-analyses,
open data can bring research on the right track.
Open data provides a bulletproof defense
against accusation of misconduct or bad scientific practices.
Open data increases research visibility and paper citations,
and well organised,  open data does also fasten the research process.
Trustworthy results are efficiently and safely delivered,
and the research gets more chances to be published and funded.
Governments, funding agencies, universities, and publishers
have recognised the importance of opening research data.
and now, they REQUEST it, rightfully
But producing open data does not come without difficulties,
it indeed requires to modify the research workflow,
a process that does not go without pain and efforts.
But once data management has been implemented, data opening happens in a swing.
Indeed the data is then already FAIR,
difficulties got blocked by open, Findable, Accessible, Interoperable and Re-usable data.
In the end, good research always wins !
For society as well as for their careers,
researchers have to gear their data:
they must make it open and FAIR,
such that their data may fly away and save the day.